ELF for the Arm® 64-bit Architecture (AArch64)

Document number: IHI 0056D_beta, current through AArch64 ABI release 2018Q4

Date of Issue: 31st December 2018

Preamble

ILP32 Beta

This document is a beta proposal for ILP32 extensions to ELF for AArch64. All significant ILP32 changes are highlighted in yellow. Feedback welcome through your normal channels.

Abstract

This document describes the use of the ELF binary file format in the Application Binary Interface (ABI) for the Arm 64-bit architecture.

Keywords

ELF, AArch64 ELF, ...

How to find the latest release of this specification or report a defect in it

Please check the Arm Developer site (https://developer.arm.com/products/software-development-tools/specifications) for a later release if your copy is more than one year old.

Please report defects in this specification to arm dot eabi at arm dot com.

Licence

THE TERMS OF YOUR ROYALTY FREE LIMITED LICENCE TO USE THIS ABI SPECIFICATION ARE GIVEN IN Your licence to use this specification (Arm contract reference LEC-ELA-00081 V2.0). PLEASE READ THEM CAREFULLY.

BY DOWNLOADING OR OTHERWISE USING THIS SPECIFICATION, YOU AGREE TO BE BOUND BY ALL OF ITS TERMS. IF YOU DO NOT AGREE TO THIS, DO NOT DOWNLOAD OR USE THIS SPECIFICATION. THIS ABI SPECIFICATION IS PROVIDED "AS IS" WITH NO WARRANTIES (SEE Your licence to use this specification FOR DETAILS).

Non-Confidential Proprietary Notice

This document is protected by copyright and other related rights and the practice or implementation of the information contained in this document may be protected by one or more patents or pending patent applications. No part of this document may be reproduced in any form by any means without the express prior written permission of Arm. No license, express or implied, by estoppel or otherwise to any intellectual property rights is granted by this document unless specifically stated.

Your access to the information in this document is conditional upon your acceptance that you will not use or permit others to use the information for the purposes of determining whether implementations infringe any third party patents.

THIS DOCUMENT IS PROVIDED "AS IS". ARM PROVIDES NO REPRESENTATIONS AND NO WARRANTIES, EXPRESS, IMPLIED OR STATUTORY, INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, SATISFACTORY QUALITY, NON-INFRINGEMENT OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE WITH RESPECT TO THE DOCUMENT. For the avoidance of doubt, Arm makes no representation with respect to, and has undertaken no analysis to identify or understand the scope and content of, patents, copyrights, trade secrets, or other rights.

This document may include technical inaccuracies or typographical errors.

TO THE EXTENT NOT PROHIBITED BY LAW, IN NO EVENT WILL ARM BE LIABLE FOR ANY DAMAGES, INCLUDING WITHOUT LIMITATION ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL, PUNITIVE, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES, HOWEVER CAUSED AND REGARDLESS OF THE THEORY OF LIABILITY, ARISING OUT OF ANY USE OF THIS DOCUMENT, EVEN IF ARM HAS BEEN ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGES.

This document consists solely of commercial items. You shall be responsible for ensuring that any use, duplication or disclosure of this document complies fully with any relevant export laws and regulations to assure that this document or any portion thereof is not exported, directly or indirectly, in violation of such export laws. Use of the word "partner" in reference to Arm's customers is not intended to create or refer to any partnership relationship with any other company. Arm may make changes to this document at any time and without notice.

If any of the provisions contained in these terms conflict with any of the provisions of any click through or signed written agreement covering this document with Arm, then the click through or signed written agreement prevails over and supersedes the conflicting provisions of these terms. This document may be translated into other languages for convenience, and you agree that if there is any conflict between the English version of this document and any translation, the terms of the English version of the Agreement shall prevail.

The Arm corporate logo and words marked with ® or ™ are registered trademarks or trademarks of Arm Limited (or its subsidiaries) in the US and/or elsewhere. All rights reserved. Other brands and names mentioned in this document may be the trademarks of their respective owners. Please follow Arm's trademark usage guidelines at http://www.arm.com/company/policies/trademarks.

Copyright © [2018] Arm Limited or its affiliates. All rights reserved.

Arm Limited. Company 02557590 registered in England. 110 Fulbourn Road, Cambridge, England CB1 9NJ. LES-PRE-20349

Contents

Contents

ELF for the Arm® 64-bit Architecture (AArch64)

Preamble

ILP32 Beta
Abstract
Keywords
How to find the latest release of this specification or report a defect in it
Licence
Non-Confidential Proprietary Notice
Contents

About this document

Change control
References
Terms and abbreviations
Your licence to use this specification

About This Specification

ELF Class variants

Platform standards (Example Only)

Linux Platform ABI (example only)

Object Files

Introduction
ELF Header
Sections
String Table
Symbol Table
Weak Symbols
Relocation

Program Loading and Dynamic Linking

Program Header
Program Property
Program Loading
Dynamic Linking

About this document

Change control

Current status and anticipated changes

The following support level definitions are used by the Arm ABI specifications:

ReleaseArm considers this specification to have enough implementations, which have received sufficient testing, to verify that it is correct. The details of these criteria are dependent on the scale and complexity of the change over previous versions: small, simple changes might only require one implementation, but more complex changes require multiple independent implementations, which have been rigorously tested for cross-compatibility. Arm anticipates that future changes to this specification will be limited to typographical corrections, clarifications and compatible extensions.
BetaArm considers this specification to be complete, but existing implementations do not meet the requirements for confidence in its release quality. Arm may need to make incompatible changes if issues emerge from its implementation.
AlphaThe content of this specification is a draft, and Arm considers the likelihood of future incompatible changes to be significant.

The ELF32 variant is at "Beta" release quality.

All other content in this document is at the Release quality level.

Change history

Issue | Date | By | Change
00bet3 | 20th December 2011 | LS | Beta release
1.0 | 22nd May 2013 | RE | First public release
1.1-beta | 6th November 2013 | JP | ILP32 Beta
2018Q4 | 31st December 2018 | OS | Typographical changes

References

This document refers to, or is referred to by, the following documents.

Ref | External reference or URL | Title
AAELF64 | Source for this document | ELF for the Arm 64-bit Architecture (AArch64).
AAPCS64 | IHI 0055 | Procedure Call Standard for the Arm 64-bit Architecture
Addenda32 | IHI 0045 | Addenda to, and Errata in, the ABI for the Arm Architecture
LSB | http://www.linuxbase.org/ | Linux Standards Base
SCO-ELF | http://www.sco.com/developers/gabi/ | System V Application Binary Interface - DRAFT
LINUX_ABI | https://github.com/hjl-tools/linux-abi/wiki | Linux Extensions to gABI
SYM-VER | http://people.redhat.com/drepper/symbol-versioning | GNU Symbol Versioning
TLSDESC | http://www.fsfla.org/~lxoliva/writeups/TLS/paper-lk2006.pdf | TLS Descriptors for Arm. Original proposal document

Terms and abbreviations

The ABI for the Arm 64-bit Architecture uses the following terms and abbreviations.

A32The instruction set named Arm in the Armv7 architecture; A32 uses 32-bit fixed-length instructions.
A64The instruction set available when in AArch64 state.
AAPCS64Procedure Call Standard for the Arm 64-bit Architecture (AArch64)
AArch32The 32-bit general-purpose register width state of the Armv8 architecture, broadly compatible with the Armv7-A architecture.
AArch64The 64-bit general-purpose register width state of the Armv8 architecture.
ABI

Application Binary Interface:

The specifications to which an executable must conform in order to execute in a specific execution environment. For example, the

Linux ABI for the Arm Architecture

.
A particular aspect of the specifications to which independently produced relocatable files must conform in order to be statically linkable and executable. For example, the C++ ABI for the Arm Architecture, ELF for the Arm Architecture, ...

Arm-based... based on the Arm architecture ...
ELF32An ELF object file with a class of ELFCLASS32
ELF64An ELF object file with a class of ELFCLASS64
ILP32SysV-like data model where int, long int and pointer are 32-bit
LP64SysV-like data model where int is 32-bit, but long int and pointer are 64-bit.
Q-o-IQuality of Implementation - a quality, behavior, functionality, or mechanism not required by this standard, but which might be provided by systems conforming to it. Q-o-I is often used to describe the tool-chain-specific means by which a standard requirement is met.
T32The instruction set named Thumb in the Armv7 architecture; T32 uses 16-bit and 32-bit instructions.

Other terms may be defined when first used.

Your licence to use this specification

IMPORTANT: THIS IS A LEGAL AGREEMENT ("LICENCE") BETWEEN YOU (AN INDIVIDUAL OR SINGLE ENTITY WHO IS RECEIVING THIS DOCUMENT DIRECTLY FROM ARM LIMITED) ("LICENSEE") AND ARM LIMITED ("ARM") FOR THE SPECIFICATION DEFINED IMMEDIATELY BELOW. BY DOWNLOADING OR OTHERWISE USING IT, YOU AGREE TO BE BOUND BY ALL OF THE TERMS OF THIS LICENCE. IF YOU DO NOT AGREE TO THIS, DO NOT DOWNLOAD OR USE THIS SPECIFICATION.

"Specification" means, and is limited to, the version of the specification for the Applications Binary Interface for the Arm Architecture comprised in this document. Notwithstanding the foregoing, "Specification" shall not include (i) the implementation of other published specifications referenced in this Specification; (ii) any enabling technologies that may be necessary to make or use any product or portion thereof that complies with this Specification, but are not themselves expressly set forth in this Specification (e.g. compiler front ends, code generators, back ends, libraries or other compiler, assembler or linker technologies; validation or debug software or hardware; applications, operating system or driver software; RISC architecture; processor microarchitecture); (iii) maskworks and physical layouts of integrated circuit designs; or (iv) RTL or other high level representations of integrated circuit designs.

Use, copying or disclosure by the US Government is subject to the restrictions set out in subparagraph (c)(1)(ii) of the Rights in Technical Data and Computer Software clause at DFARS 252.227-7013 or subparagraphs (c)(1) and (2) of the Commercial Computer Software - Restricted Rights at 48 C.F.R. 52.227-19, as applicable.

This Specification is owned by Arm or its licensors and is protected by copyright laws and international copyright treaties as well as other intellectual property laws and treaties. The Specification is licensed not sold.

Subject to the provisions of Clauses 2 and 3, Arm hereby grants to LICENSEE, under any intellectual property that is (i) owned or freely licensable by Arm without payment to unaffiliated third parties and (ii) either embodied in the Specification or Necessary to copy or implement an applications binary interface compliant with this Specification, a perpetual, non-exclusive, non-transferable, fully paid, worldwide limited licence (without the right to sublicense) to use and copy this Specification solely for the purpose of developing, having developed, manufacturing, having manufactured, offering to sell, selling, supplying or otherwise distributing products which comply with the Specification.
THIS SPECIFICATION IS PROVIDED "AS IS" WITH NO WARRANTIES EXPRESS, IMPLIED OR STATUTORY, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY WARRANTY OF SATISFACTORY QUALITY, MERCHANTABILITY, NONINFRINGEMENT OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. THE SPECIFICATION MAY INCLUDE ERRORS. Arm RESERVES THE RIGHT TO INCORPORATE MODIFICATIONS TO THE SPECIFICATION IN LATER REVISIONS OF IT, AND TO MAKE IMPROVEMENTS OR CHANGES IN THE SPECIFICATION OR THE PRODUCTS OR TECHNOLOGIES DESCRIBED THEREIN AT ANY TIME.
This Licence shall immediately terminate and shall be unavailable to LICENSEE if LICENSEE or any party affiliated to LICENSEE asserts any patents against Arm, Arm affiliates, third parties who have a valid licence from Arm for the Specification, or any customers or distributors of any of them based upon a claim that a LICENSEE (or LICENSEE affiliate) patent is Necessary to implement the Specification. In this Licence; (i) "affiliate" means any entity controlling, controlled by or under common control with a party (in fact or in law, via voting securities, management control or otherwise) and "affiliated" shall be construed accordingly; (ii) "assert" means to allege infringement in legal or administrative proceedings, or proceedings before any other competent trade, arbitral or international authority; (iii) "Necessary" means with respect to any claims of any patent, those claims which, without the appropriate permission of the patent owner, will be infringed when implementing the Specification because no alternative, commercially reasonable, non-infringing way of implementing the Specification is known; and (iv) English law and the jurisdiction of the English courts shall apply to all aspects of this Licence, its interpretation and enforcement. The total liability of Arm and any of its suppliers and licensors under or in relation to this Licence shall be limited to the greater of the amount actually paid by LICENSEE for the Specification or US$10.00. The limitations, exclusions and disclaimers in this Licence shall apply to the maximum extent allowed by applicable law.

Arm Contract reference LEC-ELA-00081 V2.0 AB/LS (9 March 2005)

About This Specification

This specification provides the processor-specific definitions required by ELF [SCO-ELF] for AArch64-based systems.

The ELF specification is part of the larger Unix System V (SysV) ABI specification where it forms Object Files and Program Loading and Dynamic Linking. However, the ELF specification can be used in isolation as a generic object and executable format. Platform standards (Example Only) covers ELF related matters that are platform specific.

Object Files and Program Loading and Dynamic Linking are structured to correspond to chapters 4 and 5 of the ELF specification. Specifically:

Object Files covers object files and relocations
Program Loading and Dynamic Linking covers program loading and dynamic linking.

ELF Class variants

Two different pointer sizes are supported by this specification, which result in two very similar but different ELF definitions.

64-bit Pointers, ELF64

Code and data using 64-bit pointers are contained in an ELF object file with a class of ELFCLASS64.
Referred to as ELF64 in this specification.
Pointer-size is 64 bits.
Suitable for use by the LP64 variant of [AAPCS64]

32-bit Pointers, ELF32 (Beta)

Code and data using 32-bit pointers is contained in an ELF object file with a class of ELFCLASS32.
Referred to as ELF32 in this specification.
Pointer-size is 32 bits.
Suitable for use by the ILP32 variant of [AAPCS64]

Note

Interlinking is not supported between the ELF32 and ELF64 variants.

Platform standards (Example Only)

We expect that each operating system that adopts components of this ABI specification will specify additional requirements and constraints that must be met by application code in binary form and the code-generation tools that generate such code.

As an example of the kind of issue that must be addressed Linux Platform ABI (example only), below, lists some of the issues addressed by the Linux Standard Base [LSB] specifications.

Linux Platform ABI (example only)

Symbol Versioning

The Linux ABI uses the GNU-extended Solaris symbol versioning mechanism [SYM-VER].

Concrete data structure descriptions can be found in /usr/include/sys/link.h (Solaris), /usr/include/elf.h (Linux), in the Linux Standard Base specifications [LSB], and in Drepper's paper [SYM-VER].

A binary file intended to be specific to Linux shall set the EI_OSABI field to the value required by Linux [LSB].

Program Linkage Table (PLT) Sequences and Usage Models

Symbols for which a PLT entry must be generated

A PLT entry implements a long-branch to a destination outside of this executable file. In general, the static linker knows only the name of the destination. It does not know its address. Such a location is called an imported location or imported symbol.

SysV-based Dynamic Shared Objects (DSOs) (e.g. for Linux) also require functions exported from an executable file to have PLT entries. In effect, exported functions are treated as if they were imported, so that their definitions can be overridden (pre-empted) at dynamic link time.

A linker must generate a PLT entry for each candidate symbol cited by a relocation directive that relocates an AArch64 B/BL-class instruction (Call and Jump relocations). For a Linux/SysV DSO, each STB_GLOBAL symbol with STV_DEFAULT visibility is a candidate.

Overview of PLT entry code generation

A PLT entry must be able to branch any distance. This is typically achieved by loading the destination address from the corresponding Global Object Table (GOT) entry.

On-demand dynamic linking constrains the code sequences that can be generated for a PLT entry. Specifically, there is a requirement from the dynamic linker for certain registers to contain certain values. Typically these are:

The address or index of the of not-yet-linked PLT entry.
The return address of the call to the PLT entry.

The register interface to the dynamic linker is specified by the host operating system.

Object Files

Introduction

Registered Vendor Names

Various symbols and names may require a vendor-specific name to avoid the potential for name-space conflicts. The list of currently registered vendors and their preferred short-hand name is given in Table 4-1, Registered Vendors. Tools developers not listed are requested to co-ordinate with Arm to avoid the potential for conflicts.

Table 4-1, Registered Vendors

Name | Vendor
aeabi | Reserved to the ABI for the Arm Architecture (EABI pseudo-vendor)
AnonXyz anonXyz | Reserved to private experiments by the Xyz vendor. Guaranteed not to clash with any registered vendor name.
ARM | Arm Ltd (Note: the company, not the processor).
cxa | C++ ABI pseudo-vendor
FSL | Freescale Semiconductor Inc.
GHS | Green Hills Systems
gnu | GNU compilers and tools (Free Software Foundation)
iar | IAR Systems
intel | Intel Corporation
ixs | Intel Xscale
llvm | The LLVM/Clang projects
PSI | PalmSource Inc.
RAL | Rowley Associates Ltd
somn | SOMNIUM Technologies Limited.
TASKING | Altium Ltd.
TI | TI Inc.
tls | Reserved for use in thread-local storage routines.
WRS | Wind River Systems.

To register a vendor prefix with Arm, please E-mail your request to arm.eabi at arm.com.

ELF Header

The ELF header provides a number of fields that assist in interpretation of the file. Most of these are specified in the base standard. The following fields have Arm-specific meanings.

e_machineAn object file conforming to this specification must have the value EM_AARCH64 (183, 0xB7).
e_entry

The base ELF specification requires this field to be zero if an application does not have an entry point. Nonetheless, some applications may require an entry point of zero (for example, via a reset vector).

A platform standard may specify that an executable file always has an entry point, in which case e_entry specifies that entry point, even if zero.

e_flagsThere are no processor-specific flags so this field shall contain zero.

ELF Identification

The 16-byte ELF identification (e_ident) provides information on how to interpret the file itself. The following values shall be used on Arm systems

EI_CLASS

For object files (executable, shared and relocatable) the EI_CLASS shall be:

ELFCLASS64 for an ELF64 object file.
ELFCLASS32 for an ELF32 object file (Beta).

EI_DATAThis field may be either ELFDATA2LSB or ELFDATA2MSB. The choice will be governed by the default data order in the execution environment.
I_OSABIThis field shall be zero unless the file uses objects that have flags which have OS-specific meanings (for example, it makes use of a section index in the range SHN_LOOS through SHN_HIOS).

Sections

Special Section Indexes

No processor-specific special section indexes are defined. All processor-specific values are reserved to future revisions of this specification.

Section Types

The defined processor-specific section types are listed in Table 4-2, Processor specific section types. All other processor-specific values are reserved to future revisions of this specification.

Table 4-2, Processor specific section types

Name | Value | Comment
SHT_AARCH64_ATTRIBUTES | 0x70000003 | Reserved for Object file compatibility attributes

Section Attribute Flags

There are no processor-specific section attribute flags defined. All processor-specific values are reserved to future revisions of this specification.

Merging of objects in sections with SHF_MERGE

In a section with the SHF_MERGE flag set, duplicate used objects may be merged and unused objects may be removed. An object is used if:

A relocation directive addresses the object via the section symbol with a suitable addend to point to the object.
A relocation directive addresses a symbol within the section. The used object is the one addressed by the symbol irrespective of the addend used.

Special Sections

Table 4-3, AArch64 special sections lists the special sections defined by this ABI.

Table 4-3, AArch64 special sections

Name | Type | Attributes
.ARM.attributes | SHT_AARCH64_ATTRIBUTES | none
.note.gnu.property | SHT_NOTE | SHF_ALLOC

.ARM.attributes names a section that contains build attributes. See Build Attributes.

.note.gnu.property names a section that holds a program property note. See [LINUX_ABI] for more information.

Additional special sections may be required by some platforms standards.

Section Alignment

There is no minimum alignment required for a section. Sections containing code must be at least 4-byte aligned. Platform standards may set a limit on the maximum alignment that they can guarantee (normally the minimum page size supported by the platform).

Build Attributes

Build attributes are encoded in a section of type SHT_AARCH64_ATTRIBUTES, and name .ARM.attributes.

Build attributes are unnecessary when a platform ABI operating system is fully specified. At this time no public build attributes have been defined for AArch64, however, software development tools are free to use attributes privately. For an introduction to AArch32 build attributes see [Addenda32].

String Table

There are no processor-specific extensions to the string table.

Symbol Table

There are no processor-specific symbol types or symbol bindings. All processor-specific values are reserved to future revisions of this specification.

Weak Symbols

There are two forms of weak symbol:

A weak reference — This is denoted by:

st_shndx=SHN_UNDEF, ELF64_ST_BIND()=STB_WEAK.
st_shndx=SHN_UNDEF, ELF32_ST_BIND()=STB_WEAK (Beta).

A weak definition — This is denoted by:

st_shndx!=SHN_UNDEF, ELF64_ST_BIND()=STB_WEAK.
st_shndx!=SHN_UNDEF, ELF32_ST_BIND()=STB_WEAK (Beta).

Weak References

Libraries are not searched to resolve weak references. It is not an error for a weak reference to remain unsatisfied.

During linking, the symbol value of an undefined weak reference is:

Zero if the relocation type is absolute
The address of the place if the relocation type is pc-relative.

See Relocation for further details.

Weak Definitions

A weak definition does not change the rules by which object files are selected from libraries. However, if a link set contains both a weak definition and a non-weak definition, the non-weak definition will always be used.

Symbol Types

All code symbols exported from an object file (symbols with binding STB_GLOBAL) shall have type STT_FUNC. All extern data objects shall have type STT_OBJECT. No STB_GLOBAL data symbol shall have type STT_FUNC. The type of an undefined symbol shall be STT_NOTYPE or the type of its expected definition.

The type of any other symbol defined in an executable section can be STT_NOTYPE. A linker is only required to provide long-branch and PLT support for symbols of type STT_FUNC.

Symbol names

A symbol that names a C or assembly language entity should have the name of that entity. For example, a C function called calculate generates a symbol called calculate (not _calculate).

Symbol names are case sensitive and are matched exactly by linkers.

Any symbol with binding STB_LOCAL may be removed from an object and replaced with an offset from another symbol in the same section under the following conditions:

The original symbol and replacement symbol are not of type STT_FUNC, or both symbols are of type STT_FUNC.
All relocations referring to the symbol can accommodate the adjustment in the addend field (it is permitted to convert a REL type relocation to a RELA type relocation).
The symbol is not described by the debug information.
The symbol is not a mapping symbol (Mapping symbols).
The resulting object, or image, is not required to preserve accurate symbol information to permit de-compilation or other post-linking optimization techniques.
If the symbol labels an object in a section with the SHF_MERGE flag set, the relocation using symbol may be changed to use the section symbol only if the initial addend of the relocation is zero.

No tool is required to perform the above transformations; an object consumer must be prepared to do this itself if it might find the additional symbols confusing.

Note

Multiple conventions exist for the names of compiler temporary symbols (for example, ARMCC uses Lxxx.yyy, while GNU tools use .Lxxx).

Reserved symbol names

The following symbols are reserved to this and future revisions of this specification:

Local symbols (STB_LOCAL) beginning with '$'
Symbols matching the pattern non-empty-prefix$$non-empty-suffix.
Global symbols (STB_GLOBAL, STB_WEAK) beginning with '__aeabi_' (double '_' at start).

Note

Global symbols beginning with '__vendor_' (double '_' at start), where vendor is listed in Registered Vendor Names are reserved to the named vendor for the purpose of providing vendor-specific toolchain support functions.

Mapping symbols

A section of an ELF file can contain a mixture of A64 code and data. There are inline transitions between code and data at literal pool boundaries.

Linkers, file decoders and other tools need to map binaries correctly. To support this, a number of symbols, termed mapping symbols appear in the symbol table to label the start of each sequence of bytes of the appropriate class. All mapping symbols have type STT_NOTYPE and binding STB_LOCAL. The st_size field is unused and must be zero.

The mapping symbols are defined in Table 4-4, Mapping symbols. It is an error for a relocation to reference a mapping symbol. Two forms of mapping symbol are supported:

A short form that uses a dollar character and a single letter denoting the class. This form can be used when an object producer creates mapping symbols automatically. Its use minimizes string table size.
A longer form in which the short form is extended with a period and then any sequence of characters that are legal for a symbol. This form can be used when assembler files have to be annotated manually and the assembler does not support multiple definitions of symbols.

Mapping symbols defined in a section (relocatable view) or segment (executable view) define a sequence of half- open intervals that cover the address range of the section or segment. Each interval starts at the address defined by the mapping symbol, and continues up to, but not including, the address defined by the next (in address order) mapping symbol or the end of the section or segment. A section that contains instructions must have a mapping symbol defined at the beginning of the section. If a section contains only data no mapping symbol is required. A platform ABI should specify whether or not mapping symbols are present in the executable view; they will never be present in a stripped executable file.

Table 4-4, Mapping symbols

Name | Meaning

$x

$x.<any...>

| Start of a sequence of A64 instructions

$d

$d.<any...>

| Start of a sequence of data items (for example, a literal pool)

Relocation

Relocation information is used by linkers to bind symbols to addresses that could not be determined when the binary file was generated. Relocations are classified as Static or Dynamic.

A static relocation relocates a place in an ELF relocatable file (e_type = ET_REL); a static linker processes it.

A dynamic relocation is designed to relocate a place in an ELF executable file or dynamic shared object (e_type = ET_EXEC, ET_DYN) and to be handled by a dynamic linker, program loader, or other post-linking tool (dynamic linker henceforth).

A dynamic linker need only process dynamic relocations; a static linker must handle any defined relocation.

Dynamic relocations are designed to be processed quickly.

There are a small number of dynamic relocations whose codes are contiguous.
Dynamic relocations relocate simple places and do not need complex field extraction or insertion.

A static linker either:

Fully resolves a relocation directive.
Or, generates a dynamic relocation from it for processing by a dynamic linker.

A well-formed executable file or dynamic shared object has no static relocations after static linking.

Relocation codes

The relocation codes for AArch64 are divided into four categories:

Mandatory relocations that must be supported by all static linkers.
Platform-specific relocations required by specific platform ABIs.
Private relocations that are guaranteed never to be allocated in future revisions of this specification, but which must never be used in portable object files.
Unallocated relocations that are reserved for use in future revisions of this specification.

Addends and PC-bias

A binary file may use REL or RELA relocations or a mixture of the two (but multiple relocations of the same place must use only one type).

The initial addend for a REL-type relocation is formed according to the following rules.

If the relocation relocates data (Static Data relocations) the initial value in the place is sign-extended to 64 bits.
If the relocation relocates an instruction the immediate field of the instruction is extracted, scaled as required by the instruction field encoding, and sign-extended to 64 bits.

A RELA format relocation must be used if the initial addend cannot be encoded in the place.

There is no PC bias to accommodate in the relocation of a place containing an instruction that formulates a PC- relative address. The program counter reflects the address of the currently executing instruction.

Relocation types

Tables in the following sections list the relocation codes for AArch64 and record the following.

The relocation code which is stored in the ELF64_R_TYPE or ELF32_R_TYPE component of the r_info field.
The preferred mnemonic name for the relocation. This has no significance in a binary file.
The relocation operation required. This field describes how a symbol and addend are processed by a linker. It does not describe how an initial addend value is extracted from a place (Addends and PC-bias) or how the resulting relocated value is inserted or encoded into a place.
A comment describing the kind of place that can be relocated, the part of the result value inserted into the place, and whether or not field overflow should be checked.

Relocation names and class

A mnemonic name class is used to distinguish between ELF64 and ELF32 relocation names.

ELF64 relocations have <CLS> = AARCH64, e.g. R_AARCH64_ABS32
ELF32 relocations have <CLS> = AARCH64_P32, where P32 denotes the pointer size, e.g. R_AARCH64_P32_ABS32 (Beta)

Note

Within this document <CLS> is not expanded in instances where only a single relocation name exists.

Relocation codes

References to relocation codes are disambiguated in the following way:

ELF64 relocation codes are bounded by parentheses: ( ).
ELF32 relocation codes are bounded by brackets: [ ].

Static relocation codes for ELF64 object files begin at (257); dynamic ones at (1024). Both (0) and (256) should be accepted as values of R_AARCH64_NONE, the null relocation.

Static relocation codes for ELF32 object files begin at [1]; dynamic ones at [180].

All unallocated type codes are reserved for future allocation.

Relocation operations

The following nomenclature is used in the descriptions of relocation operations:

S (when used on its own) is the address of the symbol.
A is the addend for the relocation.
P is the address of the place being relocated (derived from r_offset).
X is the result of a relocation operation, before any masking or bit-selection operation is applied
Page(expr) is the page address of the expression expr, defined as (expr & ~0xFFF). (This applies even if the machine page size supported by the platform has a different value.)
GOT is the address of the Global Offset Table, the table of code and data addresses to be resolved at dynamic link time. The GOT and each entry in it must be, 64-bit aligned for ELF64 or 32-bit aligned for ELF32.
GDAT(S+A) represents a pointer-sized entry in the GOT for address S+A. The entry will be relocated at run time with relocation R_<CLS>_GLOB_DAT(S+A).
G(expr) is the address of the GOT entry for the expression expr.
Delta(S) if S is a normal symbol, resolves to the difference between the static link address of S and the execution address of S. If S is the null symbol (ELF symbol index 0), resolves to the difference between the static link address of P and the execution address of P.
Indirect(expr) represents the result of calling expr as a function. The result is the return value from the function that is returned in r0. The arguments passed to the function are defined by the platform ABI.
[msb:lsb] is a bit-mask operation representing the selection of bits in a value. The bits selected range from lsb up to msb inclusive. For example, 'bits [3:0]' represents the bits under the mask 0x0000000F. When range checking is applied to a value, it is applied before the masking operation is performed.

The value written into a target field is always reduced to fit the field. It is Q-o-I whether a linker generates a diagnostic when a relocated value overflows its target field.

Relocation types whose names end with "_NC" are non-checking relocation types. These must not generate diagnostics in case of field overflow. Usually, a non-checking type relocates an instruction that computes one of the less significant parts of a single value computed by a group of instructions (Group relocations). Only the instruction computing the most significant part of the value can be checked for field overflow because, in general, a relocated value will overflow the fields of instructions computing the less significant parts. Some non-checking relocations may, however, be expected to check for correct alignment of the result; the notes explain when this is permitted. In ELF32 relocations an overflow check of -2^31 <= X < 2^31 or 0 <= X < 2^31 is equivalent to no check (i.e. 'None').

In ELF32 (Beta) relocations additional care must be taken when relocating an ADRP instruction which effectively uses a signed 33-bit PC-relative offset to generate a 32-bit address. The following relocations apply to ADRP:

R_<CLS>_ADR_PREL_PG_HI21,
R_<CLS>_ADR_GOT_PAGE,
R_<CLS>_TLSGD_ADR_PAGE21,
R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ADR_PAGE21,
R_<CLS>_TLSIE_ADR_GOTTPREL_PAGE21,
R_<CLS>_TLSDESC_ADR_PAGE21

Static miscellaneous relocations

R_<CLS>_NONE (null relocation code) records that the section containing the place to be relocated depends on the section defining the symbol mentioned in the relocation directive in a way otherwise invisible to a static linker. The effect is to prevent removal of sections that might otherwise appear to be unused.

Table 4-5, Null relocation codes

ELF64 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Comment
0 | 0 | R_<CLS>_NONE | None |
256 | - | withdrawn | None | Treat as R_<CLS>_NONE.

Static Data relocations

See also Table 4-13, GOT-relative data relocations.

Table 4-6, Data relocations

ELF64 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Overflow check
257 | - | R_<CLS>_ABS64 | S + A | None
258 | 1 | R_<CLS>_ABS32 | S + A | -2^31 <= X < 2^32
259 | 2 | R_<CLS>_ABS16 | S + A | -2^15 <= X < 2^16
260 | - | R_<CLS>_PREL64 | S + A - P | None
261 | 3 | R_<CLS>_PREL32 | S + A - P | -2^31 <= X < 2^32
262 | 4 | R_<CLS>_PREL16 | S + A - P | -2^15 <= X < 2^16

These overflow ranges permit either signed or unsigned narrow values to be created from the intermediate result viewed as a 64-bit signed integer. If the place is intended to hold a narrow signed value and INTn_MAX < X <= UINTn_MAX, no overflow will be detected but the positive result will be interpreted as a negative value.

Static AArch64 relocations

The following tables record single instruction relocations and relocations that allow a group or sequence of instructions to compute a single relocated value.

Table 4-7, Group relocations to create a 16-, 32-, 48-, or 64-bit unsigned data value or address inline

ELF64 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Comment
263 | 5 | R_<CLS>_MOVW_UABS_G0 | S + A | Set a MOVZ immediate field to bits [15:0] of X; check that 0 <= X < 2^16
264 | 6 | R_<CLS>_MOVW_UABS_G0_NC | S + A | Set a MOVK immediate field to bits [15:0] of X. No overflow check
265 | 7 | R_<CLS>_MOVW_UABS_G1 | S + A | Set a MOVZ immediate field to bits [31:16] of X; check that 0 <= X < 2^32
266 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_UABS_G1_NC | S + A | Set a MOVK immediate field to bits [31:16] of X. No overflow check
267 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_UABS_G2 | S + A | Set a MOVZ immediate field to bits [47:32] of X; check that 0 <= X < 2^48
268 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_UABS_G2_NC | S + A | Set a MOVK immediate field to bits [47:32] of X. No overflow check
269 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_UABS_G3 | S + A | Set a MOV[KZ] immediate field to bits [63:48] of X (no overflow check needed)

Note

Non-checking (_NC) forms relocate MOVK; checking forms relocate MOVZ except R_<CLS>_MOVW_UABS_G3, which can relocate either.

Table 4-8, Group relocations to create a 16, 32, 48, or 64 bit signed data or offset value inline

ELF64 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Comment
270 | 8 | R_<CLS>_MOVW_SABS_G0 | S + A | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate field using bits [15:0] of X (see notes below); check -2^16 <= X < 2^16
271 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_SABS_G1 | S + A | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate field using bits [31:16] of X (see notes below); check -2^32 <= X < 2^32
272 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_SABS_G2 | S + A | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate field using bits [47:32] of X (see notes below); check -2^48 <= X < 2^48

Note

These checking forms relocate MOVN or MOVZ.

X >= 0: Set the instruction to MOVZ and its immediate field to the selected bits of X.

X < 0: Set the instruction to MOVN and its immediate field to NOT (selected bits of X).

Table 4-9, Relocations to generate 19, 21 and 33 bit PC-relative addresses

ELF64 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Comment
273 | 9 | R_<CLS>_ LD_PREL_LO19 | S + A - P | Set a load-literal immediate value to bits [20:2] of X; check that -2^20 <= X < 2^20
274 | 10 | R_<CLS>_ ADR_PREL_LO21 | S + A - P | Set an ADR immediate value to bits [20:0] of X; check that -2^20 <= X < 2^20
275 | 11 | R_<CLS>_ ADR_PREL_PG_HI21 | Page(S+A)-Page(P) | Set an ADRP immediate value to bits [32:12] of the X; check that -2^32 <= X < 2^32
276 | - | R_<CLS>_ ADR_PREL_PG_HI21_NC | Page(S+A)-Page(P) | Set an ADRP immediate value to bits [32:12] of the X. No overflow check
277 | 12 | R_<CLS>_ ADD_ABS_LO12_NC | S + A | Set an ADD immediate value to bits [11:0] of X. No overflow check. Used with relocations ADR_PREL_PG_HI21 and ADR_PREL_PG_HI21_NC
278 | 13 | R_<CLS>_ LDST8_ABS_LO12_NC | S + A | Set an LD/ST immediate value to bits [11:0] of X. No overflow check. Used with relocations ADR_PREL_PG_HI21 and ADR_PREL_PG_HI21_NC
284 | 14 | R_<CLS>_ LDST16_ABS_LO12_NC | S + A | Set an LD/ST immediate value to bits [11:1] of X. No overflow check
285 | 15 | R_<CLS>_ LDST32_ABS_LO12_NC | S + A | Set the LD/ST immediate value to bits [11:2] of X. No overflow check
286 | 16 | R_<CLS>_ LDST64_ABS_LO12_NC | S + A | Set the LD/ST immediate value to bits [11:3] of X. No overflow check
299 | 17 | R_<CLS>_ LDST128_ABS_LO12_NC | S + A | Set the LD/ST immediate value to bits [11:4] of X. No overflow check

Note

Relocations (284, 285, 286 and 299) or [14, 15, 16, 17] are intended to be used with R_<CLS>_ADR_PREL_PG_HI21 (275) or [11] so they pick out the low 12 bits of the address and, in effect, scale that by the access size. The increased address range provided by scaled addressing is not supported by these relocations because the extra range is unusable in conjunction with R_<CLS>_ADR_PREL_PG_HI21.

Although overflow must not be checked, a linker should check that the value of X is aligned to a multiple of the datum size.

Table 4-10, Relocations for control-flow instructions - all offsets are a multiple of 4

ELF64 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Comment
279 | 18 | R_<CLS>_TSTBR14 | S+A-P | Set the immediate field of a TBZ/TBNZ instruction to bits [15:2] of X; check -2^15 <= X < 2^15
280 | 19 | R_<CLS>_CONDBR19 | S+A-P | Set the immediate field of a conditional branch instruction to bits [20:2] of X; check -2^20 <= X< 2^20
282 | 20 | R_<CLS>_JUMP26 | S+A-P | Set a B immediate field to bits [27:2] of X; check that -2^27 <= X < 2^27
283 | 21 | R_<CLS>_CALL26 | S+A-P | Set a CALL immediate field to bits [27:2] of X; check that -2^27 <= X < 2^27

Table 4-11, Group relocations to create a 16, 32, 48, or 64 bit PC-relative offset inline

ELF64 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Comment
287 | 22 | R_<CLS>_MOVW_PREL_G0 | S+A-P | Set a MOV[NZ]immediate field to bits [15:0] of X (see notes below)
288 | 23 | R_<CLS>_MOVW_PREL_G0_NC | S+A-P | Set a MOVK immediate field to bits [15:0] of X. No overflow check
289 | 24 | R_<CLS>_MOVW_PREL_G1 | S+A-P | Set a MOV[NZ]immediate field to bits [31:16] of X (see notes below)
290 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_PREL_G1_NC | S+A-P | Set a MOVK immediate field to bits [31:16] of X. No overflow check
291 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_PREL_G2 | S+A-P | Set a MOV[NZ]immediate value to bits [47:32] of X (see notes below)
292 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_PREL_G2_NC | S+A-P | Set a MOVK immediate field to bits [47:32] of X. No overflow check
293 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_PREL_G3 | S+A-P | Set a MOV[NZ]immediate value to bits [63:48] of X (see notes below)

Note

Non-checking (_NC) forms relocate MOVK; checking forms relocate MOVN or MOVZ.

X >= 0: Set the instruction to MOVZ and its immediate value to the selected bits of X; for relocation R_..._Gn, check in ELF64 that X < {G0: 2^16, G1: 2^32, G2: 2^48} (no check for R_..._G3); in ELF32 only check X < 2^16 for R_..._G0.

X < 0: Set the instruction to MOVN and its immediate value to NOT (selected bits of X); for relocation R_..._Gn, check in ELF64 that -{G0: 2^16, G1: 2^32, G2: 2^48} <= X (no check for R_..._G3); in ELF32 only check that -2^16 <= X for R_..._G0.

Table 4-12, Group relocations to create a 16, 32, 48, or 64 bit GOT-relative offsets inline

ELF64 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Comment
300 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_GOTOFF_G0 | G(GDAT(S+A)) -GOT | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate field to bits [15:0] of X (see notes below)
301 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_GOTOFF_G0_NC | G(GDAT(S+A)) -GOT | Set a MOVK immediate field to bits [15:0] of X. No overflow check
302 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_GOTOFF_G1 | G(GDAT(S+A)) -GOT | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate value to bits [31:16] of X (see notes below)
303 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_GOTOFF_G1_NC | G(GDAT(S+A)) -GOT | Set a MOVK immediate value to bits [31:16] of X. No overflow check
304 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_GOTOFF_G2 | G(GDAT(S+A)) -GOT | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate value to bits [47:32] of X (see notes below)
305 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_GOTOFF_G2_NC | G(GDAT(S+A)) -GOT | Set a MOVK immediate value to bits [47:32] of X. No overflow check
306 | - | R_<CLS>_MOVW_GOTOFF_G3 | G(GDAT(S+A)) -GOT | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate value to bits [63:48] of X (see notes below)

Note

Non-checking (_NC) forms relocate MOVK; checking forms relocate MOVN or MOVZ.

Table 4-13, GOT-relative data relocations

ELF64 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Comment
307 | - | R_<CLS>_GOTREL64 | S+A-GOT | Set the data to a 64-bit offset relative to the GOT.
308 | - | R_<CLS>_GOTREL32 | S+A-GOT | Set the data to a 32-bit offset relative to GOT, treated as signed; check that -2^31 <= X < 2^31

Table 4-14, GOT-relative instruction relocations

ELF6 4 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Comment
309 | 25 | R_<CLS>_GOT_LD_PREL19 | G(GDAT(S+A))- P | Set a load-literal immediate field to bits [20:2] of X; check -2^20 <= X < 2^20
310 | - | R_<CLS>_LD64_GOTOFF_LO15 | G(GDAT(S+A))- GOT | Set a LD/ST immediate field to bits [14:3] of X; check that 0 <= X < 2^15, X&7 = 0
311 | 26 | R_<CLS>_ADR_GOT_PAGE | Page(G(GDAT(S+A)))-Page(P) | Set the immediate value of an ADRP to bits [32:12] of X; check that -2^32 <= X < 2^32
312 | - | R_<CLS>_LD64_GOT_LO12_NC | G(GDAT(S+A)) | Set the LD/ST immediate field to bits [11:3] of X. No overflow check; check that X&7 = 0
- | 27 | R_<CLS>_LD32_GOT_LO12_NC | G(GDAT(S+A)) | Set the LD/ST immediate field to bits [11:2] of X. No overflow check; check that X&3 = 0
313 | - | R_<CLS>_LD64_GOTPAGE_LO15 | G(GDAT(S+A))-Page(GOT) | Set the LD/ST immediate field to bits [14:3] of X; check that 0 <= X < 2^15, X&7 = 0
- | 28 | R_<CLS>_LD32_GOTPAGE_LO14 | G(GDAT(S+A))-Page(GOT) | Set the LD/ST immediate field to bits [13:2] of X; check that 0 <= X < 2^14, X&3 = 0

Call and Jump relocations

There is one relocation code (R_<CLS>_CALL26) for function call (BL) instructions and one (R_<CLS>_JUMP26) for jump (B) instructions.

A linker may use a veneer (a sequence of instructions) to implement a relocated branch if the relocation is either

R_<CLS>_CALL26 or R_<CLS>_JUMP26 and:

The target symbol has type STT_FUNC.
Or, the target symbol and relocated place are in separate sections input to the linker.
Or, the target symbol is undefined (external to the link unit).

In all other cases a linker shall diagnose an error if relocation cannot be effected without a veneer. A linker generated veneer may corrupt registers IP0 and IP1 [AAPCS64] and the condition flags, but must preserve all other registers. Linker veneers may be needed for a number of reasons, including, but not limited to:

Target is outside the addressable span of the branch instruction (+/- 128MB).
Target address will not be known until run time, or the target address might be pre-empted.

In some systems indirect calls may also use veneers in order to support dynamic linkage that preserves pointer comparability (all reference to the function resolve to the same address).

On platforms that do not support dynamic pre-emption of symbols an unresolved weak reference to a symbol relocated by R_<CLS>_CALL26 shall be treated as a jump to the next instruction (the call becomes a no-op). The behaviour of R_<CLS>_JUMP26 in these conditions is not specified by this standard.

Group relocations

A relocation code whose name ends in _Gn or _Gn_NC (n = 0, 1, 2, 3) relocates an instruction in a group of instructions that generate a single value or address (see Table 4-7, Table 4-8, Table 4-11, Table 4-12). Each such relocation relocates one instruction in isolation, with no need to determine all members of the group at link time.

These relocations operate by performing the relocation calculation then extracting a field from the result X. Generating the field for a Gn relocation directive starts by examining the residual value Yn after the bits of abs(X) corresponding to less significant fields have been masked off from X. If M is the mask specified in the table recording the relocation directive, Yn = abs(X) & ~((M & -M) - 1).

Overflow checking is performed on Yn unless the name of the relocation ends in "_NC".

Finally the bit-field of X specified in the table (those bits of X picked out by 1-bits in M) is encoded into the instruction's literal field as specified in the table. In some cases other instruction bits may need to be changed according to the sign of X.

For "MOVW" type relocations it is the assembler's responsibility to encode the hw bits (bits 21 and 22) to indicate the bits in the target value that the immediate field represents.

Proxy-generating relocations

A number of relocations generate proxy locations that are then subject to dynamic relocation. The proxies are normally gathered together in a single table, called the Global Offset Table or GOT. Table 4-12, Group relocations to create a 16, 32, 48, or 64 bit GOT-relative offsets inline and Table 4-14, GOT-relative instruction relocations list the relocations that generate proxy entries.

All of the GOT entries generated by these relocations are subject to dynamic relocations (Dynamic relocations).

Relocations for thread-local storage

The static relocations needed to support thread-local storage in a SysV-type environment are listed in tables in the following subsections

In addition to the terms defined in Relocation types, the tables listing the static relocations relating to thread-local storage use the following terms in the column named Operation.

GLDM(S) represents a consecutive pair of pointer-sized entries in the GOT for the load module index of the symbol S. The first pointer-sized entry will be relocated with R_<CLS>_TLS_DTPMOD(S); the second pointer-sized entry will contain the constant 0.
GTLSIDX(S,A) represents a consecutive pair of pointer-sized entries in the GOT. The entry contains a tls_index structure describing the thread-local variable located at offset A from thread-local symbol S. The first pointer-sized entry will be relocated with R_<CLS>_TLS_DTPMOD(S), the second pointer-sized entry will be relocated with R_<CLS>_TLS_DTPREL(S+A).
GTPREL(S+A) represents a pointer-sized entry in the GOT for the offset from the current thread pointer (TP) of the thread-local variable located at offset A from the symbol S``. The entry will be relocated with R_<CLS>_TLS_TPREL(S+A).
GTLSDESC(S+A) represents a consecutive pair of pointer-sized entries in the GOT which contain a tlsdesc structure describing the thread-local variable located at offset A from thread-local symbol S. The first entry holds a pointer to the variable's TLS descriptor resolver function and the second entry holds a platform-specific offset or pointer. The pair of pointer-sized entries will be relocated with R_<CLS>_TLSDESC(S+A).
LDM(S) resolves to the load module index of the symbol S.
DTPREL(S+A) resolves to the offset from its module's TLS block of the thread local variable located at offset A from thread-local symbol S.
TPREL(S+A) resolves to the offset from the current thread pointer (TP) of the thread local variable located at offset A from thread-local symbol S.
TLSDESC(S+A) resolves to a contiguous pair of pointer-sized values, as created by GTLSDESC(S+A).

General Dynamic thread-local storage model

Table 4-15, General Dynamic TLS relocations

ELF64 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Comment
512 | 80 | R_<CLS>_TLSGD_ ADR_PREL21 | G(GTLSIDX(S,A)) - P | Set an ADR immediate field to bits [20:0] of X; check -2^20 <= X < 2^20
513 | 81 | R_<CLS>_TLSGD_ ADR_PAGE21 | Page(G(GTLSIDX(S,A))) - Page(P) | Set an ADRP immediate field to bits [32:12] of X; check -2^32 <= X < 2^32
514 | 82 | R_<CLS>_TLSGD_ ADD_LO12_NC | G(GTLSIDX(S,A)) | Set an ADD immediate field to bits [11:0] of X. No overflow check
515 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSGD_ MOVW_G1 | G(GTLSIDX(S,A)) - GOT | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate field to bits [31:16] of X (see notes below)
516 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSGD_ MOVW_G0_NC | G(GTLSIDX(S,A)) - GOT | Set a MOVK immediate field to bits [15:0] of X. No overflow check

Note

Non-checking (_NC) MOVW forms relocate MOVK; checking forms relocate MOVN or MOVZ.

X >= 0: Set the instruction to MOVZ and its immediate value to the selected bits of X; check that X < 2^32.

X < 0: Set the instruction to MOVN and its immediate value to NOT (selected bits of X); check that -2^32 <= X.

Local Dynamic thread-local storage model

Table 4-16, Local Dynamic TLS relocations

ELF64 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Comment
517 | 83 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ ADR_PREL21 | G(GLDM(S))) - P | Set an ADR immediate field to bits [20:0] of X; check -2^20 <= X < 2^20
518 | 84 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ ADR_PAGE21 | Page(G(GLDM(S)))-Page(P) | Set an ADRP immediate field to bits [32:12] of X; check -2^32 <= X < 2^32
519 | 85 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ ADD_LO12_NC | G(GLDM(S)) | Set an ADD immediate field to bits [11:0] of X. No overflow check
520 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ MOVW_G1 | G(GLDM(S)) - GOT | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate field to bits [31:16] of X (see notes below)
521 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ MOVW_G0_NC | G(GLDM(S)) - GOT | Set a MOVK immediate field to bits [15:0] of X. No overflow check
522 | 86 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ LD_PREL19 | G(GLDM(S)) - P | Set a load-literal immediate field to bits [20:2] of X; check -2^20 <= X < 2^20
523 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ MOVW_DTPREL_G2 | DTPREL(S+A) | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate field to bits [47:32] of X (see notes below)
524 | 87 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ MOVW_DTPREL_G1 | DTPREL(S+A) | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate field to bits [31:16] of X (see notes below)
525 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ MOVW_DTPREL_G1_NC | DTPREL(S+A) | Set a MOVK immediate field to bits [31:16] of X. No overflow check
526 | 88 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ MOVW_DTPREL_G0 | DTPREL(S+A) | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate field to bits [15:0] of X (see notes below)
527 | 89 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ MOVW_DTPREL_G0_NC | DTPREL(S+A) | Set a MOVK immediate field to bits [15:0] of X. No overflow check
528 | 90 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ ADD_DTPREL_HI12 | DTPREL(S+A) | Set an ADD immediate field to bits [23:12] of X; check 0 <= X < 2^24
529 | 91 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ ADD_DTPREL_LO12 | DTPREL(S+A) | Set an ADD immediate field to bits [11:0] of X; check 0 <= X < 2^12
530 | 92 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ ADD_DTPREL_LO12_NC | DTPREL(S+A) | Set an ADD immediate field to bits [11:0] of X. No overflow check
531 | 93 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ LDST8_DTPREL_LO12 | DTPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:0] of X; check 0 <= X < 2^12
532 | 94 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ LDST8_DTPREL_LO12_NC | DTPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:0] of X. No overflow check
533 | 95 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ LDST16_DTPREL_LO12 | DTPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:1] of X; check 0 <= X < 2^12
534 | 96 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ LDST16_DTPREL_LO12_NC | DTPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:1] of X. No overflow check
535 | 97 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ LDST32_DTPREL_LO12 | DTPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:2] of X; check 0 <= X < 2^12
536 | 98 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ LDST32_DTPREL_LO12_NC | DTPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:2] of X. No overflow check
537 | 99 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ LDST64_DTPREL_LO12 | DTPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:3] of X; check 0 <= X < 2^12
538 | 100 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ LDST64_DTPREL_LO12_NC | DTPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:3] of X. No overflow check
572 | 101 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ LDST128_DTPREL_LO12 | DTPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:4] of X; check 0 <= X < 2^12
573 | 102 | R_<CLS>_TLSLD_ LDST128_DTPREL_LO12_ NC | DTPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:4] of X. No overflow check

Note

Non-checking (_NC) MOVW forms relocate MOVK; checking forms relocate MOVN or MOVZ.

X >= 0: Set the instruction to MOVZ and its immediate value to the selected bits S; for relocation R_..._Gn, check in ELF64 that X < {G0: 2^16, G1: 2^32, G2: 2^48} (no check for R_..._G3); in ELF32 only check that X < 2^16 for R_..._G0.

X < 0: Set the instruction to MOVN and its immediate value to NOT (selected bits of); for relocation R_..._Gn, check in ELF64 that -{G0: 2^16, G1: 2^32, G2: 2^48} <= X (no check for R_..._G3); in ELF32 only check that -2^16 <= X for R_..._G0.

For scaled-addressing relocations (533-538, 572 and 573) or [95-102] a linker should check that X is a multiple of the datum size.

Initial Exec thread-local storage model

Table 4-17, Initial Exec TLS relocations

ELF64 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Comment
539 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSIE_ MOVW_GOTTPREL_G1 | G(GTPREL(S+A)) - GOT | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate field to bits [31:16] of X (see notes below)
540 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSIE_ MOVW_GOTTPREL_G0_NC | G(GTPREL(S+A)) - GOT | Set MOVK immediate to bits [15:0] of X. No overflow check
541 | 103 | R_<CLS>_TLSIE_ ADR_GOTTPREL_PAGE21 | Page(G(GTPREL(S+A))) - Page(P) | Set an ADRP immediate field to bits [32:12] of X; check -2^32 <= X < 2^32
542 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSIE_ LD64_GOTTPREL_LO12_NC | G(GTPREL(S+A)) | Set an LD offset field to bits [11:3] of X. No overflow check; check that X&7=0
- | 104 | R_<CLS>_TLSIE_ LD32_GOTTPREL_LO12_NC | G(GTPREL(S+A)) | Set an LD offset field to bits [11:2] of X. No overflow check; check that X&3=0
543 | 105 | R_<CLS>_TLSIE_ LD_GOTTPREL_PREL19 | G(GTPREL(S+A)) - P | Set a load-literal immediate to bits [20:2] of X; check -2^20 <= X < 2^20

Note

Non-checking (_NC) MOVW forms relocate MOVK; checking forms relocate MOVN or MOVZ.

Local Exec thread-local storage model

Table 4-18, Local Exec TLS relocations

ELF64 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Comment
544 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ MOVW_TPREL_G2 | TPREL(S+A) | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate field to bits [47:32] of X (see notes below)
545 | 106 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ MOVW_TPREL_G1 | TPREL(S+A) | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate field to bits [31:16] of X (see notes below)
546 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ MOVW_TPREL_G1_NC | TPREL(S+A) | Set a MOVK immediate field to bits [31:16] of X. No overflow check
547 | 107 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ MOVW_TPREL_G0 | TPREL(S+A) | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate field to bits [15:0] of X (see notes below)
548 | 108 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ MOVW_TPREL_G0_NC | TPREL(S+A) | Set a MOVK immediate field to bits [15:0] of X. No overflow check
549 | 109 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ ADD_TPREL_HI12 | TPREL(S+A) | Set an ADD immediate field to bits [23:12] of X; check 0 <= X < 2^24.
550 | 110 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ ADD_TPREL_LO12 | TPREL(S+A) | Set an ADD immediate field to bits [11:0] of X; check 0 <= X < 2^12.
551 | 111 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ ADD_TPREL_LO12_NC | TPREL(S+A) | Set an ADD immediate field to bits [11:0] of X. No overflow check
552 | 112 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ LDST8_TPREL_LO12 | TPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:0] of X; check 0 <= X < 2^12.
553 | 113 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ LDST8_TPREL_LO12_NC | TPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:0] of X. No overflow check
554 | 114 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ LDST16_TPREL_LO12 | TPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:1] of X; check 0 <= X < 2^12
555 | 115 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ LDST16_TPREL_LO12_NC | TPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:1] of X. No overflow check
556 | 116 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ LDST32_TPREL_LO12 | TPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:2] of X; check 0 <= X < 2^12
557 | 117 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ LDST32_TPREL_LO12_NC | TPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:2] of X. No overflow check
558 | 118 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ LDST64_TPREL_LO12 | TPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:3] of X; check 0 <= X < 2^12
559 | 119 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ LDST64_TPREL_LO12_NC | TPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:3] of X. No overflow check
570 | 120 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ LDST128_TPREL_LO12 | TPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:4] of X; check 0 <= X < 2^12
571 | 121 | R_<CLS>_TLSLE_ LDST128_TPREL_LO12_NC | TPREL(S+A) | Set a LD/ST offset field to bits [11:4] of X. No overflow check

Note

Non-checking (_NC) MOVW forms relocate MOVK; checking forms relocate MOVN or MOVZ.

For scaled-addressing relocations (554-559, 570 and 571) or [112-121] a linker should check that X is a multiple of the datum size.

Thread-local storage descriptors

Table 4-19, TLS descriptor relocations

ELF64 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Comment
560 | 122 | R_<CLS>_TLSDESC_ LD_PREL19 | G(GTLSDESC(S+A)) - P | Set a load-literal immediate to bits [20:2]; check -220 <= X < 2^20; check X & 3 = 0.
561 | 123 | R_<CLS>_TLSDESC_ ADR_PREL21 | G(GTLSDESC(S+A) - P | Set an ADR immediate field to bits [20:0]; check -220 <= X < 2^20.
562 | 124 | R_<CLS>_TLSDESC_ ADR_PAGE21 | Page(G(GTLSDESC(S+A))) - Page(P) | Set an ADRP immediate field to bits [32:12] of X; check -2^32 <= X < 2^32.
563 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSDESC_ LD64_LO12 | G(GTLSDESC(S+A)) | Set an LD offset field to bits [11:3] of X. No overflow check; check X & 7 = 0.
- | 125 | R_<CLS>_TLSDESC_ LD32_LO12 | G(GTLSDESC(S+A)) | Set an LD offset field to bits [11:2] of X. No overflow check; check X & 3 = 0.
564 | 126 | R_<CLS>_TLSDESC_ ADD_LO12 | G(GTLSDESC(S+A)) | Set an ADD immediate field to bits [11:0] of X. No overflow check.
565 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSDESC_ OFF_G1 | G(GTLSDESC(S+A)) - GOT | Set a MOV[NZ] immediate field to bits [31:16] of X; check -2^32 <= X < 2^32. See notes below.
566 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSDESC_ OFF_G0_NC | G(GTLSDESC(S+A)) - GOT | Set a MOVK immediate field to bits [15:0] of X. No overflow check.
567 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSDESC_ LDR | None | For relaxation only. Must be used to identify an LDR instruction which loads the TLS descriptor function pointer for S + A if it has no other relocation.
568 | - | R_<CLS>_TLSDESC_ ADD | None | For relaxation only. Must be used to identify an ADD instruction which computes the address of the TLS Descriptor for S + A if it has no other relocation.
569 | 127 | R_<CLS>_TLSDESC_ CALL | None | For relaxation only. Must be used to identify a BLR instruction which performs an indirect call to the TLS descriptor function for S + A.

Note

X >= 0: Set the instruction to MOVZ and its immediate value to the selected bits of X.

X < 0: Set the instruction to MOVN and its immediate value to NOT (selected bits of X).

Relocation codes R_<CLS>_TLSDESC_LDR, R_<CLS>_TLSDESC_ADD and R_<CLS>_TLSDESC_CALL are needed to permit linker optimization of TLS descriptor code sequences to use Initial-exec or Local-exec TLS sequences; this can only be done if all relevant uses of TLS descriptors are marked to permit accurate relaxation. Object producers that are unable to satisfy this requirement must generate traditional General-dynamic TLS sequences using the relocations described in General Dynamic thread-local storage model. The details of TLS descriptors are beyond the scope of this specification; a general introduction can be found in [TLSDESC].

Dynamic relocations

The dynamic relocations for those execution environments that support only a limited number of run-time relocation types are listed in Table 4-20, Dynamic relocations. The enumeration of dynamic relocations commences at (1024) or [180] and the range is compact.

Table 4-20, Dynamic relocations

ELF64 Code | ELF32 Code | Name | Operation | Comment
1024 | 180 | R_<CLS>_COPY | | See note below.
1025 | 181 | R_<CLS>_GLOB_DAT | S + A | See note below
1026 | 182 | R_<CLS>_JUMP_SLOT | S + A | See note below
1027 | 183 | R_<CLS>_RELATIVE | Delta(S) + A | See note below
1028 | | R_<CLS>_TLS_DTPREL64 | DTPREL(S+A) |
| 184 | R_<CLS>_TLS_DTPREL | DTPREL(S+A) |
1029 | | R_<CLS>_TLS_DTPMOD64 | LDM(S) |
| 185 | R_<CLS>_TLS_DTPMOD | LDM(S) |
1030 | | R_<CLS>_TLS_TPREL64 | TPREL(S+A) |
| 186 | R_<CLS>_TLS_TPREL | TPREL(S+A) |
1031 | 187 | R_<CLS>_TLSDESC | TLSDESC(S+A) | Identifies a TLS descriptor to be filled
1032 | 188 | R_<CLS>_IRELATIVE | Indirect(Delta(S) + A) | See note below.

With the exception of R_<CLS>_COPY all dynamic relocations require that the place being relocated is an 8-byte aligned 64-bit data location in ELF64 or a 4-byte aligned 32-bit data location in ELF32.

R_<CLS>_COPY may only appear in executable ELF files where e_type is set to ET_EXEC. The effect is to cause the dynamic linker to locate the target symbol in a shared library object and then to copy the number of bytes specified by its st_size field to the place. The address of the place is then used to pre-empt all other references to the specified symbol. It is an error if the storage space allocated in the executable is insufficient to hold the full copy of the symbol. If the object being copied contains dynamic relocations then the effect must be as if those relocations were performed before the copy was made.

R_<CLS>_COPY is normally only used in SysV type environments where the executable is not position- independent and references by the code and read-only data sections cannot be relocated dynamically to refer to an object that is defined in a shared library.

The need for copy relocations can be avoided if a compiler generates all code references to such objects indirectly through a dynamically relocatable location and if all static data references are placed in relocatable regions of the image. In practice, this is difficult to achieve without source-code annotation. A better approach is to avoid defining static global data in shared libraries.

R_<CLS>_GLOB_DAT relocates a GOT entry used to hold the address of a (data) symbol which must be resolved at load time.

R_<CLS>_JUMP_SLOT is used to mark code targets that will be executed.

On platforms that support dynamic binding the relocations may be performed lazily on demand.
The initial value stored in the place is the offset to the entry sequence stub for the dynamic linker. It must be adjusted during initial loading by the offset of the load address of the segment from its link address.
Addresses stored in the place of these relocations may not be used for pointer comparison until the relocation after has been resolved.
Because the initial value of the place is not related to the ultimate target of a R_<CLS>_JUMP_SLOT relocation the addend A of such a REL-type relocation shall be zero rather than the initial content of the place. A platform ABI shall prescribe whether or not the r_addend field of such a RELA-type relocation is honored. (There may be security-related reasons not to do so).

R_<CLS>_RELATIVE represents a relative adjustment to the place based on the load address of the object relative to its original link address. All symbols defined in the same segment will have the same relative adjustment. If S is the null symbol (ELF symbol index 0) then the adjustment is based on the segment defining the place. On systems where all segments are mapped contiguously the adjustment will be the same for each reloction, thus adjustment never needs to resolve the symbol. This relocation represents an optimization; it can be used to replace R_<CLS>_GLOB_DAT when the symbol resolves to the current dynamic shared object.

R_<CLS>_IRELATIVE represents a dynamic selection of the place's resolved value. The means by which this relocation is generated is platform specific, as are the conditions that must hold when resolving takes place.

Private and platform-specific relocations

Private relocations for vendor experiments:

0xE000 to 0xEFFF for ELF64
0xE0 to 0xEF for ELF32

Platform ABI defined relocations:

0xF000 to 0xFFFF for ELF64
0xF0 to 0xFF for ELF32

Platform ABI relocations can only be interpreted when the EI_OSABI field is set to indicate the Platform ABI governing the definition.

All of the above codes will not be assigned by any future version of this standard.

Unallocated relocations

All unallocated relocation types are reserved for use by future revisions of this specification.

Idempotency

All RELA type relocations are idempotent. They may be reapplied to the place and the result will be the same. This allows a static linker to preserve full relocation information for an image by converting all REL type relocations into RELA type relocations.

Note

A REL type relocation can only be idempotent if the original addend was zero and if subsequent re-linking assumes that REL relocations have zero for all addends.

Program Loading and Dynamic Linking

This section provides details of AArch64-specific definitions and changes relating to executable images.

Program Header

The Program Header provides a number of fields that assist in interpretation of the file. Most of these are specified in the base standard [SCO-ELF]. The following fields have AArch64-specific meanings.

p_typeTable 5-1, Processor-specific segment types lists the processor-specific segment types.

Table 5-1, Processor-specific segment types

Name | p_type | Meaning
PT_AARCH64_ARCHEXT | 0x70000000 | Reserved for architecture compatibility information
PT_AARCH64_UNWIND | 0x70000001 | Reserved for exception unwinding tables

A segment of type PT_AARCH64_ARCHEXT (if present) contains information describing the architecture capabilities required by the executable file. Not all platform ABIs require this segment; the Linux ABI does not. If the segment is present it must appear before segment of type PT_LOAD.

PT_AARCH64_UNWIND (if present) describes the location of a program's exception unwind tables.

p_flagsThere are no AArch64-specific flags.

Platform architecture compatibility data

At this time this ABI specifies no generic platform architecture compatibility data.

Program Property

The following processor-specific program property types [LINUX_ABI] are defined:

Table 5-2, Program Property Type

Name | Value
GNU_PROPERTY_AARCH64_FEATURE_1_AND | 0xc0000000

GNU_PROPERTY_AARCH64_FEATURE_1_AND represents a bitfield of individual features. It has a single 4-byte integer for the pr_data field. For each feature, a static linker must set its corresponding bit if all input relocatable object files have the feature bit set.

The following bits are defined for GNU_PROPERTY_AARCH64_FEATURE_1_AND:

Table 5-3, GNU_PROPERTY_AARCH64_FEATURE_1_AND Bit Flags

Name | Value
GNU_PROPERTY_AARCH64_FEATURE_1_BTI | 1U << 0
GNU_PROPERTY_AARCH64_FEATURE_1_PAC | 1U << 1

GNU_PROPERTY_AARCH64_FEATURE_1_BTI This indicates that all executable sections are compatible with Branch Target Identification mechanism. An executable or shared object with this bit set is requried to generate Custom PLTs with BTI instruction.

GNU_PROPERTY_AARCH64_FEATURE_1_PAC This indicates that all executable sections have Return Address Signing enabled. An executable or shared object with this bit set can generate Custom PLTs with a PAC instruction.

Program Loading

Process GNU_PROPERTY_AARCH64_FEATURE_1_BTI

If Branch Target Identification mechanism is enabled on a processor then the Guard Page (GP) bit must be disabled on the memory image of loaded executable segments of executables and shared objects that do not have GNU_PROPERTY_AARCH64_FEATURE_1_BTI set, before execution is transferred to them.

Dynamic Linking

Custom PLTs

To support Branch Target Identification mechinasm, in the presense of a GNU_PROPERTY_AARCH64_FEATURE_1_BTI all PLT entries generated by the linker must have a BTI instruction as the first instruction. The linker must add the DT_AARCH64_BTI_PLT (Table 5-4, AArch64 specific dynamic array tags) tag to the dynamic section.
To support Pointer Authentication, PLT entries generated by the linker can have an authenticating instruction as the final instruction before branching back. The linker must add the DT_AARCH64_PAC_PLT (Table 5-4, AArch64 specific dynamic array tags) tag to the dynamic section.
If the linker generates custom PLT entries with both BTI and PAC instructions, it must add both DT_AARCH64_BTI_PLT and DT_AARCH64_PAC_PLT tags to the dynamic section.

Dynamic Section

AArch64 specifies the following processor-specific dynamic array tags.

Table 5-4, AArch64 specific dynamic array tags

Name | Value | d_un | Executable | Shared Object
DT_AARCH64_BTI_PLT | 0x70000001 | d_val | Platform specific | Platform Specific
DT_AARCH64_PAC_PLT | 0x70000003 | d_val | Platform specific | Platform Specific

DT_AARCH64_BTI_PLT indicates PLTs enabled with Branch Target Identification mechanism.

DT_AARCH64_PAC_PLT indicates PLTs enabled with Pointer Authentication.

The presence of both DT_AARCH64_BTI_PLT and DT_AARCH64_PAC_PLT indicates PLTs enabled with both Branch Target Identification mechanism and Pointer Authentication.